Guide to the Lorraine Forte Photographs 1968-1992 PR 397
New-York Historical Society
Lorraine Forte photographs
1968-1992
New-York Historical Society
Forte, Lorraine, 1950-
PR 397
42 photograph(s) in 1 flat box.
Views of streetscapes, buildings, rooftops, billboards, amusements, and statuary in Manhattan, Brooklyn, and Coney Island, taken by New York City-based photographer Lorraine Forte. Includes two images of protestors at the Tompkins Square Park riot of 1988. Some of the photographs appeared in Forte's book, Macchiato (2017).
Arrangement
The prints are sorted in the order in which they were received from the photographer. For ease of access, the archivist has numbered the images consecutively (in pencil, in the lower right back corner of each print), from 1 to 42, and divided them into folders with their corresponding catalog sheets:
Catalog sheet 1: prints 01-10
Catalog sheet 2: prints 11-20
Catalog sheet 3: prints 21-28
Catalog sheet 4: prints 29-34
Catalog sheet 5: prints 35-42
The photographer's descriptions are quoted as notes in the container list, below. Clarifications by the archivist are enclosed in [square brackets].
Biographical / Historical
New York City-based photographer Lorraine Forte was born in New Jersey in 1950. In addition to attending Parsons School of Design, she studied photography with Lisette Model, Larry Fink, and Inge Bondi of Magnum Consortium. Since her first solo exhibition at Princeton, New Jersey, in 1972, Forte's work has been seen at galleries in Washington, D.C., and throughout New York City and State. For more information visit the photographer's website: www.lorraineforte.com.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lorraine Forte, October 2018 (accession no. PPAC-2018-053).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains 42 black-and-white, inkjet printed photographs (each measuring 11 x 17 inches) taken by Lorraine Forte of locations in Manhattan and Brooklyn between 1968 and 1992. See the container list for self-explanatory titles and the photographer's descriptions of each view. Included are two shots of the Tompkins Square Park riot of August 6–7, 1988, when protestors clashed with police over a recently instituted 1 a.m. curfew for the previously 24-hour park. Some of the present images appeared in Forte's book, Macchiato (2017).
Inkjet prints.; Photographs.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Manhattan (New York, N.Y.); Tompkins Square (New York, N.Y.); Riots -- New York (State) -- New York.; Street photography -- New York (State) -- New York.
- [Catalog sheet 1 + prints]
  - THE FAN, 1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 01)
    Scope and Contents
    "View of a bodega on the corner of Avenue A and 12th Street through a window fan."
  - CARNIVAL, 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 02)
    "An East Village Carnival."
  - MOVIE LIGHTING, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 03)
    "East village roof looking north. A movie was being filmed and the lighting was bleaching the view and casting stark shadows."
  - DAD, 1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 04)
    "East village roof looking east. My father had just died and I was thinking of him."
  - TINSEL TOWN, 1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 05)
    "The Grace building."
    [The W. R. Grace Building is a 50-story skyscraper at 1114 Sixth Avenue, Manhattan.]
  - SPLIT, 1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 06)
    "Looking North on 9th Avenue in the 40s."
  - SNOWFLAKE, 1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 07)
    "A familiar seasonal decoration at 5th and 57th."
    [The UNICEF crystal snowflake lights the interesection of Fifth Avenue and 57th Street each December.]
  - LINE-O-TRINE, 1987 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 08)
    "Tiffany's at the same location as above [i.e., Fifth Avenue and 57th Street]. A bus is going by."
  - INDUSTRIAL AGE, 1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 09)
    "Roof view from the 40s."
  - GASETERIA, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1, Item 10)
    "The gas station at Houston and Lafayette. The Puck Building is in the background."
    [The Puck Building stands at 295-307 Lafayette Street, Manhattan.]
- [Catalog sheet 2 + prints]
  - EL TEDDY'S, 1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 11)
    "Teddy's history precedes and post dates itself."
    [Tribeca mainstay restaurant El Teddy's was located at 219 West Broadway.]
  - BILLBOARD, 1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 12)
    "View from in back of a billboard looking south onto 9th Avenue."
  - LOISAIDA FIREWORKS, 1990 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 13)
    "View of fireworks in the East River looking north from rooftop."
  - SQUARE, 1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 14)
    "Washington Square Park in the spring."
  - HALLOWEEN, 1988 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 15)
    "The Hell's Angels had a ritual of stringing skeletons across 3rd Street for Halloween. The brushwork in the sky is made by the quickly moving clouds during a time exposure."
    [The Hells Angels vacated their longtime headquarters at 77 East 3rd Street, Manhattan, in 2019.]
  - STOPLIGHT, 1986 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 16)
    "View overlooking Flatbush Avenue, Brooklyn."
  - THEY'RE IN LOVE, 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 17)
    "Statues near Grand Army Plaza."
    [The Bailey Fountain in Grand Army Plaza, Brooklyn.]
  - DISCO CARWASH, 1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 18)
    "Carwash on Flatbush Avenue, in Brooklyn."
  - MODERN AGE, 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 19)
    "Waiting for a movie to start at the Elgin Theater."
    [After renovations, the Elgin Theater, at 175 Eighth Avenue, Manhattan, reopened as the Joyce Theater in 1982.]
  - PET SHOP, 1971 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2, Item 20)
    "This is a Yorkville pet shop window."
- [Catalog sheet 3 + prints]
  - STAIRWAY, 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 21)
    "Looking up from a subway exit."
  - CHINA BOWL, 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 22)
    "Looking through their blinds onto 44th Street. A period perfect Chinese restaurant that was used for movie shoots."
    [The China Bowl was located at 152 West 44th Street in Times Square.]
  - EL DORADO, 1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 23)
    "Bumper cars in Coney Island."
    [El Dorado Bumper Cars & Arcade is located at 1215 Bowery Street, Coney Island.]
  - NIGHT OF THE LIVING AIRPORT, 1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 24)
    "The crowd after a King Crimson concert on a Pier near the Intrepid."
  - 101, 1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 25)
    "View looking down from the World Trade Center."
  - TWILIGHT ZONE, 1991 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 26)
    "The program that's on the TV."
  - APPAMATTOX [Appomattox], 1983 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 27)
    "Fireworks view from Brooklyn rooftop."
  - UNDERWEAR WARS, 1982 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3, Item 28)
    "Billboards Times Square."
- [Catalog sheet 4 + prints]
  - 220, 1985 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4, Item 29)
    "A West Village entrance."
  - UMBRELLA, 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4, Item 30)
    "50th Street between 5th and 6th Avenue."
  - 30 ROCK, 1994 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4, Item 31)
    "Compilation of two images, 30 Rockefeller Center."
    [Formerly known as the RCA Building (1933-1988), the GE Building (1988-2015), and now the Comcast Building (2015-present).]
  - THE MET, 1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4, Item 32)
    "The Metropolitan Museum of Art."
  - TOY CARS, 1984 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4, Item 33)
    "Traffic on Flatbush Avenue."
  - JOHNNY'S GOT A GARDEN, 1992 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4, Item 34)
    "12th Street Garden view."
- [Catalog sheet 5 + prints]
  - TRANCE, 1972 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 35)
    "Ride operator, Coney Island."
  - SHOOTER, 1988 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 36)
    "Coney Island."
  - SHOE SHINE, 1980 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 37)
    "A sign by a guy that set up shop near the World Trade Center."
  - HATS AND COAT, 1968 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 38)
    "Window display from 1968."
  - SUBWAY, 1981 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 39)
    "The Graffiti era."
  - EAST END HOTEL, 1969 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 40)
    "A women's hotel on East River Drive and 79th Street."
  - TOMKINS SQUARE RIOT [Tompkins Square Park riot] (image 1 of 2), 1988 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 41)
  - TOMKINS SQUARE RIOT [Tompkins Square Park riot] (image 2 of 2), 1988 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5, Item 42)